Hello everyone, so we are here with Arthur in Montreal for the HackerOne Advisory Board meeting
and he agreed to not only have an interview with me for the podcast but also show us a great bug,
actually more than one bug, about Java deserialization. We'll start by saying how to
discover it, how to notice it in a little bit different way, that is the most common giveaway,
and also how to bypass it, what to do when ysoserial doesn't work.
Hello Arthur, thank you so much for joining me for the explanation and can you please start by
telling us what made you think there's a deserialization going on, because it's a
specific bug class where you only hunt for it when you have a suspicion it exists.
So thank you for having me and thank you for the invite, I was really excited about this interview.
So in this specific case it was really awesome, in this case I first found this domain and I
did some fuzzing, after fuzzing I found this specified path with the older application inside
this path and after seeing this application I saw some requests and this request has some
a curious object in the path. So I'm not only looking for this kind of vulnerability
but when I saw this object my eyes, oh probably here it has good thing and I
reworking that, so what I see on the path was the start H4S, so this is a good
thing to stay worried when you are looking for deserialization with
vulnerability, because this start is when you have some java object
and after this java object has been compressed by gzip and after compressed by gzip
you have encoded in base64 and this object
H4S probably will be a java object. So it's a little less common one than RO0, which is the
typical but without the compression. Yeah, it's because there is a compression here, so if
in this case didn't have any compression, the path probably will be RO0 in this case.
Yeah, which of course from our perspective, from the vulnerability perspective doesn't make any
difference, just one more step for exploiting it. Yeah, so in this case you only need
when you are using the ysoserial, an example if you are using the ysoserial command, you pipe with
gzip, if you are using bash in a pipe to gzip and after that pipe to base64 and you have
the payload. So in that case, I really like an extension called Java Deserialization Scanner
I like this extension because when I have some of this kind of vulnerability, I can use
that and you need to set in the extension the path to ysoserial and with that extension you have
more abilities and you have a graphical interface to deal with the deserialization. So I like
that you are capable to set the insertion points or the place to the java object in the
extension and you are capable to set the ysoserial command in the extension too. So in
this case of this report, I set the DNS with my out of band server only to get the result
of this request. So basically this extension under the hood still uses ysoserial.
Yeah, it's a graphical interface. It's just easier to use this. Yeah, it's better. Maybe it helps if you
don't like to use commands a lot. So I like because I have this graphical interface, I can send to
Burp Suite the request. So this is important to me because sometimes when you
copy the object from the terminal, sometimes maybe it's not right or the object is not complete. So
you can use this extension to get the request complete on the Burp Suite. So I use a lot of
Burp Suite and maybe combine these two things and in that case I have the jzip compress so
I set the insertion point, put the ysoserial gadget in the extension,
compress it using gzip, and after that encode it by base64, send the request, and we have the
code. Yeah, we have the out of band. So yeah, this is a good way of getting this.
Oh, there's another thing here. Some cases when you have some problems with encoding,
an example, you have slashes and plus and equal. In this case, it was important to
encode these chars because the payload was not processed in the right way if you didn't code
these chars. So I encoded these chars and the break lines to encode changed to, I didn't
saw the name, but these chars. Yeah, so sometimes callback is enough to prove the
deserialization and sometimes it's enough to get the report triaged, but sometimes the
problem requires us to go further and it's not always as easy. Yeah, this case was
easy and the triage and the team agreed you don't need to go more far because we know
your deserialization, you prove this to us and this is a critical vulnerability.
Yeah, it's rewarded as a 10 out of 10 critical. Nice.
Yeah, so yeah, the vulnerability was triaged with the CVSS10.
Yeah, it's a lovely feeling. Yeah, it's a really good sensation.
Also, sorry to keep you waiting, but finally I can announce that again it's possible to get
access to case studies, the OAuth course and the DevTools course. The link is in the description.
Sometimes when you are facing this Java deserialization vulnerabilities, you are able
to access some gadgets like JMRP Client. It's another gadget on ysoserial, so you can use
these gadgets to try and understand if you are deserialized or not, if deserialization is
occurring or not in the backend of the application. But sometimes there is some way to fix
deserialization using the lookahead object input. I've never encountered this, to be honest.
Yeah, so sometimes when, for example, you try URL DNS works, you try JMRP Client, it works because
you have a timeout. This gadget is interesting because you didn't receive
out-of-band with URL DNS, but you can receive some connection from the server or you can see
if you receive a timeout, because sometimes your servers are blocked. And if you use JMRP Client
to test deserialization, probably if the servers are blocked or any TCP connection out-of-band
are blocked, you will be receiving timeout or 10 seconds or 12 seconds, 11 seconds.
An example, the page needs 200 milliseconds to load, but when you use that payload,
JMRP Client, the page needs 10 seconds to load or 11 seconds to load, because probably the Java is
trying to connect to your server or something and the connection didn't work, but probably
deserialization is happening here. And you have these gadgets working, but the other classes
like common collections or other things are not working, and probably there is some fix here or
maybe they use some fix using lookahead object input, because with this fix,
what Java is going to do is check if the class is allowed to deserialize or not.
So this is what this fix does. Because when you have a Java object,
in this Java object, you have the name of the class. So with this method, you check the name
of the class. Oh, probably this is a malicious class, it's not in our allow list.
If it's not in our allow list, probably it's a malicious gadget, you will not
deserialize this guy. So when we have these problems, a good way to bypass this is
using our repository called serial killer bypass gadget collection. It's a good way to bypass,
because what is happening here is a guy called Alvaro Muñoz.
I think this guy has had more reports, not only in Java, but in .NET deserialization, I think.
I don't know, but I remember to see anything like that. So this guy has this repository with a lot
of bypasses, and these bypasses are using native libraries like a bridge.
Because when lookahead method will check if the class is allowed or not to deserialize,
you have the bypass class in the front, and when the lookahead method will check,
oh, this gadget is okay, when deserialization will happen, you will execute not the class,
but the malicious gadget with the class, and you can reach the remote code execution.
So does this lookahead fix, does it look at, let's say we create an object of
allow listed class, does it also look at what objects does this class create,
or does it only look at the first one?
Yeah, probably it's the first one, the importance of the first one.
So we only need like one bridge here, and then once we are there, we can do whatever we want.
Probably, maybe it can be more complicated than we are talking about, maybe it's that.
Look at the first, if the first is allowed, okay, you can pass,
and this first can be used to call other gadgets.
Yeah, cool.
And the gadgets are in the code of the application, because the ysoserial gadgets,
they are really code native in the libraries.
These codes are only used to get the remote code execution.
So this is the reason why there are a lot of common collections,
common collections 2, 3, 4, I think there is a lot,
because these common collections maybe work in different versions of Java.
Probably, if you have ysoserial and you have a
deserialization with a possible deserialization vulnerability,
you try all to see all.
Usually you do.
Yeah, you try all.
The same thing with the SerialKillerBipedGadgetCollection, I showed to you that example.
We use the command ping, and with the ping we use ping,
GadgetClass, GadgetBypass in our out-of-band server,
and we create a Python script with all the ysoserial gadgets
and all the bypasses in the SerialKiller,
and we write all the commands to generate all the payloads and send them through there,
and after that we just save a lot of ping with all the bypasses working in the web server.
Yeah, so you have the RCE.
Was this one also rewarded as a 10 out of 10 critical?
Yeah, so this case I showed you, it was more funny because it was an engagement,
and after that we need to deal with the SOC,
because we are working in a pentest,
and deal with the SOC and have a lot of bypass to SOC,
and buy new domains because they are blocking our domains.
Yeah, they are blocking our domains.
We need to up new AWS instance, buy new domains,
because the idea is if the SOC allows us to continue,
when we try to close the contract with Brazil,
all these are allowed tests, and we are dealing with the SOC
because the idea is we didn't have any help from the SOC.
We do all these things bypassing the SOC and all the things we can do there.
Our out-of-band is blocked
because we only have out-of-band and didn't have persistence at that time,
so we use some commands
for example, read some file, compressing to gzip,
using xdd to convert in hexadecimal,
and a loop to break, and step by step send to our server,
and we do the reverse process to get the other file.
Yeah, it was really, really cool.
Very cool. Thank you so much for going through it.
If you enjoyed it, make sure to subscribe to also watch our full interview
that will be published two weeks after this video.
For now, thank you so much for watching and goodbye.